<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration or proffer of the Archdukes of Brabant concerning a truce betweene them and the States of the Free vnited Netherlandish Prouinces, tending to the treatie for a perpetuall peace betweene them: or for a surceasance of armes for certaine yeares. Contained in a letter sent vnto the said states. Also the ansvver and acceptance of the states of the vnited prouinces vnto the arch-dukes. Translated out of Netherlandish printed copie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16566</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119283</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854490</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854490</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19914</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16566)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19914)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1195:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration or proffer of the Archdukes of Brabant concerning a truce betweene them and the States of the Free vnited Netherlandish Prouinces, tending to the treatie for a perpetuall peace betweene them: or for a surceasance of armes for certaine yeares. Contained in a letter sent vnto the said states. Also the ansvver and acceptance of the states of the vnited prouinces vnto the arch-dukes. Translated out of Netherlandish printed copie.</title>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 6, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. R[aworth] for William Ferebrand, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The Yale copy has A3,4 inserted from STC 5492.2 with dedication to the Earl of Exeter.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19914:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19914:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OR PROFFER OF THE Archdukes of Brabant, concerning a <hi>truce betweene them and the</hi> States <hi>of the Free vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Netherlandiſh Prouinces, tending to the treatie for a perpetuall Peace betweene them: or for a ſurcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of Armes for certaine yeares. Contained in a Letter ſent vnto the ſaid States.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo the Anſvver and Acceptance of the States of the vnited Prouinces vnto the Arch-dukes.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Netherlandiſh Printed copie.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON Printed by R. R. for <hi>William Ferebrand,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Popes-head Alley. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19914:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19914:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> TO THE RIGHT Honourable the Earle of Exceter, Knight of the moſt Honorable order of the Garter: and one of the Lordes of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties moſt Honorable priuie Counſel. <hi>R. P. wiſheth all encreaſe of Honor and endleſſe bappineſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay it pleaſe your Hon.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The obſeruation which this world begets, may teach experience truly to report, that <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> are for the moſt part grovvne ſo cold, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the hoteſt Sun-ſhine of our <hi>Profeſsion,</hi> as that deſpiſed <hi>Pouertie,</hi> though addicted to the <hi>Religious exerciſe</hi> of endeuors co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, is in the beſt employment (vvhich ſeemes vvith greateſt <hi>Fauor</hi> to <hi>ſmile</hi> vpon his <hi>Hope</hi>) ſo coldly recompenced, as that <hi>poore vnpitied deiected miſerable Pouertie</hi> knovves neither <hi>Meanes</hi> nor <hi>Place</hi> hovv or vvhere to vvarme it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19914:3"/>
Vnhappie I, in this beſt time of greateſt happines, who being as I am a Poore diſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, hated, ſcorned, and vnreſpected <hi>Souldier</hi> ſo vnfortunate as no commended meanes, though many vſed, with confirmation both of <hi>loue</hi> and <hi>Loyaltie,</hi> can bee of power from diſpayres <hi>Gulfe,</hi> to raiſe a <hi>Spirit</hi> drowned, in worſt of miſery: but were I not indeered vnto thoſe by heauen made mine, who are indeed, to me, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> life, more deare from who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is no way to run, vnleſſe in me, ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be diſolued, I would aſſuredly by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens aſsiſtance in ſome honeſt <hi>War</hi> vvith vſe of <hi>Armes,</hi> giue to my life ſo long as I ſhould liue, a liuing maintenance: but novv <hi>Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> in my natiue home, vnſeperably <hi>Yoakt</hi> vvith leane-fac't pouertie. I haue experience to conclude that as it is moſt certaine <hi>Pax procreat Bellum,</hi> ſo is it no leſſe true, that a coufirmed <hi>Peace, Non amat Fillios belli,</hi> vntill ſhe hath need of them.</p>
            <p>In this eſtate not knowing how to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d my ſelfe, <hi>Religions</hi> Lawe ſhall make my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution honeſt, &amp; though <hi>Rerum conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem mutare non poſſum,</hi> yet I will haue power to ſay <hi>Hoc poſsum magnum ſumere animam et viro forti dignum,</hi> with patience therefore
<pb facs="tcp:19914:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhal my grieued thoghts ioyfully be thrown vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my makers prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by whoſe aſsiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance I will ſtill reſolue vvith a conſtant Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to perſiſt in the proſecution of commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded deedes, for this I knovv <hi>Spes mea, Chriſto viuens, Est viuere vt ſemper viuam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, my Honorable Lord, hauing breathed forth a ſight vnto the grace of your compaſsionate reſpect: I humbly craue your Honor vvill vouchſafe, to patronize in this little booke (by me collected) not my ovvne but the vvords of that reuerend and learned <hi>Judge,</hi> the Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> vvho at his coming to <hi>Norwich,</hi> did at the <hi>Aſſiſes</hi> there vpon the bench, deliuer a charge ſo exelent as that it vvorthyly deſerues to bee continued in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall memorie, vvhich being thus produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to a publique vievv, I hope it ſhall vnto our <hi>Publickeweale</hi> remaine a vvorthy preſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, vvherein <hi>Romes</hi> champions may vvith ſhame decerne their long continued ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full practices, <hi>Puritans</hi> &amp; <hi>Siſmatickes</hi> learne to knovve vvith vvhat <hi>Iniuſtice</hi> they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbe the happineſſe of our moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie peace, our <hi>Iuſtices,</hi> inferior officers, <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,</hi> and Commons generally, may in this booke find out commended <hi>documents,</hi> and <hi>instructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> profitable as vvel directing hovv
<pb facs="tcp:19914:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>to gouern as to be gouerned: all which par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars the learned <hi>Iudge</hi> hath wiſely ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled with ſuch plauſible <hi>Oratorical</hi> wiſedomes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence, as that vvhen I heard him ſpeake, I though the <hi>Poet</hi> had iuſt cauſe to ſay, <hi>Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera lux orritur linguiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> animiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fauete: Nam dicendà bono ſunt bona verba die.</hi> If therefore in this follovving vvorke my Memory hath giuen a true inſtruction to my pen, I hope my labour ſhalbe accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted profitable, when it adminiſters a publique benefit.</p>
            <p>Thus Right Hon. <hi>Earle,</hi> vvhat I haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in performed, together vvith my moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvorthy ſelfe, I humbly referre vnto your Honoured vviſedomes conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as I vvill alvvayes reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in all humbleneſse of Dutie. <hi>R. P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19914:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The <hi>Letter of the Arch-Dukes, ſent vnto the States of the vnited</hi> Prouinces.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Archdukes, whoſe heartes moſt ſeruent and earneſt deſires en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour nothing more, then to ſee the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlandes, and all the good Inhabitants thereof at peace, and free from the miſeries of theſe continuall warres, vpon good conſiderate deliberation, declare and ſignifie by theſe preſents, that they are contented to treat with the States of the ſaid vnited Netherlandes in the ſelfe ſame qualitie, as houlding and reputing them to be free Countries, Prouinces, and States.</p>
            <p>Vpon the which, their Highneſſes not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19914:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>clayming or pretending any thing. Bee it by way of a perpetuall peace, truce, or ſurcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of armes, for twelue, fifteene, or twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares, euen to the free choyſe and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the aforeſaid States, the whole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending vpon reaſonable conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Amongſt which conditions, couenants and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, alſo ſhall be admitted, aſwell to the concluſion of a perpetual peace, as to a truce, or ſurceaſe of Armes: That each one ſhall continue to haue and remaine poſſeſſed of all that which he now inioyeth, vnleſſe that by common conſent it be conueniently other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe agreed vpon, for the better accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Highneſſes, and the ſaid Stats, togither reſpectiuely with the Netherlands, in the exchange of ſome Citties, or any other places. As alſo vpon the good order and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon trade, traffique, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>merce, &amp; conuerſation, with whatſoeuer belongeth thereunto, togither with the Interuentions, confirmation, and furtherance of what ſhall be concluded. And their Highneſſes hauing thus maturely conſidered vpon the eſtate of the vnited Prouinces, and deſiring to treat with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no otherwiſe herein then faithfully, without fraud &amp; deceit: as alſo to grant vnto the ſaid States a time of deliberatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and determine what ſhall be moſt need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt for the common good and benefit pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19914:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And are therefore contented, that thoſe perſons that they ſhall appoint for the ſaide Truce (which ſhal be born Netherlanders) ſhall aſſemble themſelues togither with the ſaid States in like number at the time and place appointed, to be choſen and limmitted by the ſaid States.</p>
            <p>And to the end that whatſoeuer is formerly rehearſed, may haue the better proceeding, be it for a perpetual peace, or the ſaid ſurceſſe their Highneſſes are contented, that for the next enſuing eight monethes, there ſhall be a general ſurceaſe of armes, all ſeiges and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſings of Citties or Fortreſſes, all Incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and deuaſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s whatſoeuer in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces and quarters, togither with a ſurcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to build any new fortreſſes, or procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in any other Hoſtile action either by ſea or land, in all the Netherlands, or at Sea, in <hi>Spaine,</hi> or elſewhere, as well in reſpect of the King, as of their Highneſſes, from the day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Anno 1607.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And vpon condition prouided, that if with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the aforeſaid time of day and moneth, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any of the parties ignorantly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking knowledge hereof, ſhould ſurpriſe or intercept any thing from the other partie, that the ſame ſhall then bee dewly repaired, and reſtitution made, ſo farre forth as the ſaid States on their partes doe allowe and approue the ſaid prouiſionall truce, within
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19914:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>eight dayes after the preſentation of theſe. And before the firſt of <hi>September</hi> next com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, they ſhal declare and ſignifie vnto their Highneſſes, (vppon the aforeſaid treatie) which is proffered touching peace, truce, or ſurceaſance of armes, togither with the time and place by them to make choiſe of, to that effect.</p>
            <argument>
               <p>Done in Bruſſels the 13. of March 1607. was Paragrafied <hi>Richardot</hi> V<hi rend="sup">t</hi>: Signed <hi>Albert, Iſabell,</hi> and vnderneath<lb/> By order of their Highneſſe <hi>Verreyken</hi> and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the Signet of their Highneſſes.</p>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:19914:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The States Generall of the vnited Prouinces, together with his Excellencie, hauing conſidered vpon the Proffers, declarations, and preſentations of the Arch-dukes, returne their Anſwer as followeth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat in the qualitie as <hi>States</hi> of Free countries and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, on the which the High and Mightie Arch-dukes pretend nothing they haue vpon good deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and with aduiſe of his Excellencie, and counſell of Eſtate, decreed and declare by theſe preſents, That they for their parts, no leſſe than the other partie, heartely wiſh nothing more, than to ſee the Netherlands deliuered, by meanes of ſome godly, honourable, and ſecure ende, from the miſeries of theſe warres. And hoping that the Arch-dukes, both in the behalfe of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> &amp; for themſelues, haue made theſe proffers, declarations, and preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſincerely and faithfully.</p>
            <p>The ſaid <hi>States</hi> Generall in the qualitie as aforeſaid, haue accepted and accept by theſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19914:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>preſents, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> declaration, and prouiſionall Truce aforeſaid, for <hi>8.</hi> moneths, beginning the <hi>20.</hi> of Aprill next comming, from all ſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſurpriſts of cities, and foretreſſes, inuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or incurſions of Prouinces and Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: together with the making of any newe Fortes or Sconces. As alſo wee receiue their farther proffers and preſentations, to communicate &amp; relate vnto thoſe to whom ſhall belong thereby to make their declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before the firſt day of September next comming, with full aſſurance that God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie will bleſſe and guide the buſines for the beſt.</p>
            <p>And thereupon the writings and bonds of the promiſed Approbation, and like declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> (according to the agreement made betweene the comitties of their Highneſſes and Ours) ſhal be diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the tenth of Aprill next enſuing. And within two, or at the fartheſt, three daies af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, deliuered, and exchanged before <hi>Lillo. Done in s'Granenhage.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19914:7"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt all the temporall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings that God of his free boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty beſtowes vpon any King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or Nation, there is not any thing more inualuable the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that heauen-bred happines, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Quietnes:</hi> it was a harmony from Angelicall voyces, at the birth of our Sauiour, when thoſe diuine Embaſſadours brought glad tidings of great ioy, pronouncing <hi>Peace on earth, and vnto all men good will:</hi> when our Sauiour departed from his Diſciples, hee left <hi>Peace</hi> with them; when hee came amongſt them after his reſurrection, the doores beeing ſhut, hee ſpake <hi>Peace</hi> vnto them: and <hi>Peace</hi> is that, without which, all other things are diſtaſtfull and vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant.</p>
            <p>What is it in this world, either for honour, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, plenty, aliance, artes, friendſhip, or any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane good, but with <hi>Peace</hi> it flowriſheth in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſun-ſhine?</p>
            <p>We our ſelues, of any Nation vnder the cope
<pb facs="tcp:19914:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>of heauen, can euidence this to the whole world, that haue had the Palme-tree ſpread ouer this Kingdome, the long raigne of a peacefull Queen, and continueth in flowriſhing ſtate the preſent raigne of her worthy ſucceſſor, who is the mirror of <hi>Peace</hi> to all Nations of the earth. But what we haue not feared, others haue moſt grieuouſly felt, eſpecially our neere neighbours, (the vnited Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands) whoſe tragedy begun by rugged warre, hath continued in bloody action, many yeares of terror; thei<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> calamities and miſeries, which of vs can be ignorant of? Engliſh eares haue heard their roaring Canons eccho in the ayre, imitating <hi>Ioues</hi> thunder, their Trumpets ſound the fatall knell of infinit thouſands, and their Drummes allarmes laden the earth with millions of dead carkaſſes.</p>
            <p>Engliſh eies haue ſeene the deuaſtations, ſpoiles, ſieges, ranſackings, &amp; flaming cities, of thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries: Engliſh liues haue beene liberally ſpent in their martiall buſineſſe, followed their fortunes, bled in their quarrels, and died in their battels.</p>
            <p>But now, after all theſe bloody affaires, this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed endleſſe warre, theſe reputed irreuocable cruelties, behold a ſtrange and admirable alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſuch implacable aduerſaries, ſhall moſt readily and willingly propound loue and amitie, offering to ſheath the ſword till it ruſt (euen a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall <hi>Peace,</hi>) or a Truce limited, or any indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency of faithfull triall.</p>
            <p>From whence proceedeth the originall of theſe deſignes? to whom muſt the efficient cauſe bee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed?
<pb facs="tcp:19914:8"/>but onely to that Almightie Peace-ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker, who hath the ruling and ordering of hearts in his owne hand, to diſpoſe of them as hee pleaſeth, be they neuer ſo potent, powerfull, or oppoſite.</p>
            <p>For as in Iuſtice hee hath a ſeuere and cruell whip of three cordes, to puniſh ſinners (to wit of <hi>Famine, Sword,</hi> and <hi>Peſtilence,</hi>) ſo in his Mercie he hath <hi>Plentie, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Health:</hi> freely to beſtow on whome his mercie ſhall pleaſe to extend them. It is to be hoped that the Lords wrath will be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed, towards them that the ſword hath deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for ſuch a long continuance of years. And that he will rather powre out his wrath and heauie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure vpon the heathen that haue not knowne him, nor called vpon his name. And it is a dutie wherunto euery Chriſtian man is obliged, to pray vnto the great God of Heauen, that hee will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue his hand of Iuſtice from his poore weake and fraile creatures, whom with one angry frown, he can at once deſtroy from the face of the earth. The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is a good and ioyfull thing, for brethren to dwell in vnity.</hi> All that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Chriſt, are taught by him, in prayer to call him father, and the ſonnes of one father muſt needs be brethren.</p>
            <p>This motion of <hi>Peace</hi> and concord (if it bee faithfull and vnfained, to preuent effuſion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian blood) is moſt honourable, and the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance thereof, of as high worthineſſe: he that made the heart knowes it, and hath the diſpoſe of it: hee that is called the Lord of Hoſts can command an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb facs="tcp:19914:9"/>to fight his battell, with terrible ſlaughter: and againe, can beyond all expectation of humane creature, ceaſe ſtearne fac't warre, with mild im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracements of ſmiling Peace.</p>
            <p>To conclude, let all bee referred to his will, who hath power, and whoſe power no mortall is able to reſiſt, and let our affections ioyne with thoſe heauenly ſouldiers, that ſounded forth <hi>Peace</hi> on earth, &amp; good will with men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <trailer type="illustration">
               <figure/>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
